"Apparently, being in love isn't enough."
“顯然，光是喜歡是不行的”
"Where does a crime
“到底怎麼樣
start and where does it end?
才算犯罪？”
Don't call me that.
別叫我老師
I don't deserve to be.
我沒資格被叫老師
I don't care what anyone says.
我不在意別人怎麼說
I love you.
我喜歡老師
Akira!
阿晶！
We're going home.
回去了
No.
不要
Akira.
阿晶
Akira!
阿晶！
Don't make me angrier.
不要讓我更生氣了
I ran a bath, you should clean your foot.
我放好洗澡水了，妳先洗洗腳吧
Shotaro.
勝太郎
I have to talk to you.
我想和你談談
About everything.
關於這一切
-That was-- -You don't have to say it.
-那是… -妳不用說
I trust you.
我相信妳
That was your student, Kuroiwa, was it?
那個學生叫黑岩，是嗎？
The one giving you all that trouble?
是讓妳一直很傷腦筋的問題學生吧？
You were trying to be a good teacher, and he dragged you in.
因為妳太努力當好老師 所以被對方牽著鼻子走了吧
But I--
可是我…
It's fine. Don't worry about it.
好了啦，別在意
Although, you should address it for his parents' sake.
但妳得好好解釋讓家長安心
You need to nip this in the bud.
妳需要儘早解決這個問題
You know,
妳知道
I'm in love with Ms. Suenaga, and I kept telling her.
我喜歡老師還一直說喜歡她
Then she also--
這樣她也會…
Don't be an idiot!
別傻了！
You're still in middle school.
你才國中而已
A child.
只是個孩子
Forget about her.
趕快忘了她吧
-No. -I'll never let you meet her again.
-不要 -我不會再讓你和她見面
-This isn't okay. -I don't care what you say.
-這是不對的 -我不管妳說什麼
No matter what you think, you won't get to be with her.
無論你怎麼想，你們也不可能交往
It's not just me, society won't allow it.
不只是媽媽，社會也不會允許
-So let it be over-- -It's not over!
-所以一切到此結束… -不會結束！
I'll marry her one day!
我以後要跟老師結婚！
Have you lost your mind!
你瘋了吧！
Go wash your face and snap out of it.
去洗把臉清醒點
What the hell, that hurt.
什麼啦，痛死了
KOSUKE SHIMAZAKI
（寄件人：島崎康介）
SHOTARO
（勝太郎）
OPEN MESSAGE
（開啟）
I just reached Osaka. I'll message you again tonight.
我剛到大阪，晚上再聯繫妳
He's a student.
他是個學生
What am I doing?
我到底在做什麼？
Messing with a student.
和學生糾纏不清
KOBOSHIDAIRA JUNIOR HIGH
（子星中學）
Hello?
喂？
It's Shioya.
我是鹽谷
Could you come to the school now?
妳現在能來學校嗎？
Yes.
是
Where is it?
在哪裡？
Your phone's not here.
你的手機不在這裡
Your mom's canceling it.
你媽拿去取消服務了
What?
什麼？
After she stops by your school.
在她去了學校之後
School?
學校？
Excuse me.
打擾了
Sit down.
坐吧
You're being accused of sexual misconduct.
妳被控訴做出淫穢行為的嫌疑
From the first day you started up until the events of last night,
從上任以來到昨晚
please tell us everything that has occurred.
請坦白說出都發生了什麼事
Looking back,
現在回想起來
from the very beginning
從一開始
he was different from the other students.
他就和其他學生不一樣
Kuroiwa.
黑岩
You okay?
你還好嗎？
Did you hit your head?
你有撞到頭嗎？
Please! You need to stop annoying me.
拜託妳不要再煩我了！
Nothing went well when I first started.
剛上任時總是處處碰壁
When I was feeling at my lowest, he…
在我最難過的時候，他…
"The good rain knows its season,
“好雨知時節
When spring arrives, it brings life."
當春乃發生”
He recited something I taught the class.
他很開心地唸起我教導的內容
He depended on me.
信任這樣的我
Kuroiwa, did you fall?
黑岩同學，你摔下來了嗎？
Did you hit your head?
你有撞到頭嗎？
Please don't come to hate me.
請不要討厭我
I'm an inexperienced teacher, when Kuroiwa showed interest in me,
我作為老師還不夠經驗 但當黑岩對我抱有好感
he gave me the support I needed.
給予我所需的支持
I was also having wedding doubts.
我對即將結婚的事也感到不安
I wasn't sure
我不確定
if it would work out.
結婚後會不會順利
So rather than face reality,
比起面對這些現實
being with Kuroiwa
跟黑岩同學在一起的時候
gave me excitement,
總會忍不住心動
and heartbreak like I was back in school.
感到揪心，彷彿回到學生時代
When Kuroiwa sensed my feelings,
當黑岩同學察覺我的心意
he was even harder to stop.
越來越無法停止
And last night,
還有昨晚
on the way home from the fireworks,
在煙火大會回程途中
I ran into him.
我碰見他了
And we kissed.
然後我們接吻了
I regret it deeply.
我很後悔
It was thoughtless
是我太粗心
and foolish.
太愚蠢了
RESIGNATION LETTER
（辭呈）
I will quit teaching.
我會辭職
I will never go near Kuroiwa again.
我不會再接近黑岩同學
When Akira was born,
阿晶出生的時候
he was 3,080 gram.
是3080公克
He became yellow,
他患了黃疸
and was taken to an incubator.
進了保溫箱
He cried through the night,
在半夜哭鬧
and was quite the handful.
讓人非常傷腦筋
When he got a high fever, and passed out after foaming at the mouth,
發高燒時，口吐白沫後失去意識
I took him to the emergency room.
我帶他衝到急診室
I thought there was an earthquake but it was just me shaking.
我還以為發生地震 結果原來是我的身體在發抖
He was a late talker,
他學說話很慢
so I'd check out three picture books from the library every week,
每週我都會去圖書館借三本繪本
reading to him every night,
每晚唸給他聽
until we both fell asleep.
直到兩人一起睡著
The reason I worked so hard every day
我像這樣每一天努力工作
raising my son the best I could
用心地養育我的兒子
was to make him a respectable person.
都是為了讓他成為出色的人
To have a good life.
讓他擁有美好的人生
Ms. Kuroiwa!
黑岩太太！
Not so you could have your way with him.
不是讓妳拿來消遣
He's not a present for you.
不是要送給妳的禮物
-Ms. Kuroiwa. -Wedding doubts?
-黑岩太太 -對結婚感到不安？
I don't care!
我才不管！
How dare you use my Akira as some play thing!
憑什麼利用我家阿晶當妳的玩物？
Who do you think you are!
妳以為妳是誰！
Your anger is justifiable. But please.
我知道您非常生氣，但是
Please refrain yourself.
請先冷靜一下
Did you think you would be allowed to make this decision for yourself?
妳認為自己能夠決定是否辭職嗎？
Kanagawa Prefecture Juvenile Protection Ordinance article 31,
《神奈川縣青少年保護育成條例》 第三十一條
"No juvenile should be subjected
“禁止對青少年做出
to a sexual act or indecent behavior."
淫穢的性行為及猥褻行為”
Such a crime will be punished.
否則將受到懲處
You have both failed as a teacher
無論是作為教師或是人
and as a person.
妳都失去資格了
The school will internally discuss your discipline.
接下來學校內部會討論妳的處分
You are to remain at home in the mean time.
在結果出來之前，妳要禁足在家
Do not come to school.
不能來學校
And do not interact with any students.
也絕不能跟任何學生接觸
Yes, ma'am.
是的
I understand.
我知道了
I am truly
真的…
sorry for everything.
非常抱歉
Oh, boy, that's hot.
哎呀，好燙
Hot.
好燙
Okay.
好的
Akira.
阿晶
I made you some cold noodles with sesame dressing.
我做了芝麻醬拌中華涼麵
Akira?
阿晶？
He got me.
被擺了一道
Ms. Suenaga!
老師！
Ms. Suenaga.
老師
Are you okay?
妳沒事吧？
-What did my Mom say? -Leave it.
-我媽說了什麼？ -不要問了
Just go home.
快回去吧
Ms. Suenaga?
老師？
Kuroiwa, what are you doing?
黑岩同學，你在做什麼？
You aren't allowed contact until her discipline is decided.
在決定她的處分之前，禁止跟她接觸
Discipline?
處分？
Your mother already left.
你母親已經回去了
You should--
你應該…
Kuroiwa!
黑岩同學！
Ms. Suenaga.
老師
What do they mean discipline? Are you quitting?
處分是什麼意思？妳要辭職嗎？
-That's right. -Will I never see you again?
-是的 -我不能再見妳了嗎？
That's right.
是
Are you marrying him?
妳要嫁給他嗎？
Sorry, just forget about me.
對不起，你忘了我吧
No.
不要
That was a mistake.
那樣是不對的
It was wrong.
那是錯的
Why?
為什麼？
Because you're fifteen!
因為你才十五歲！
-Ms. Suenaga! -Kuroiwa!
-老師！ -黑岩同學！
-Please don't make Ms. Suenaga quit!
-請不要逼老師辭職！
Please!
拜託了！
I'll quit instead! I'll drop out of school!
我會休學！我會停學！
-What are you saying? -You can't quit.
-你說什麼？ -你不可以休學
Then I won't talk to her or even look at her face!
那我不會再跟她說話 也不會再見她！
I'll give up.
我會放棄
So please, let her stay at the school.
所以請讓老師留在學校
I'm begging you!
拜託妳！
-Your girlfriend's coming? -Hey.
-你女友要來這邊啦？ -喂
You finally get to have that newlywed life you wanted.
你終於能過上期待已久的新婚生活
Sorry to move on without you.
抱歉，沒等你就先行一步了
So annoying.
真火大
But leave the wedding party to me, I give great speeches.
婚禮派對就交給我吧 我致辭很厲害哦
Thanks.
謝啦
Weird and suspicious.
很奇怪，而且很可疑
What is?
什麼事？
Last night at the fireworks,
昨晚的煙火大會
Hijiri wasn't answering your calls and was mysteriously missing.
小聖一直沒接你電話還消失了
Things were off, now this sudden turn? You're moving in together?
情況明明不太對勁 卻突然這樣了，你們要同居了？
I see.
我明白了
Don't laugh. Stop it.
不要笑
What do you want me to do?
那妳要我怎麼樣啊？
What happened last night?
昨晚發生什麼事？
Well,
其實
we talked afterwards, and Hijiri decided to quit and move here.
那之後我們好好談過 聖決定辭職並搬過來
Things just worked out this way.
是很自然地解決了
-She's quitting teaching? -Yes.
-她辭職了？ -是
When she cares about it so much?
她明明那麼認真？
This all seems fishy.
太可疑了
Which means I…
也就是說…
You know,
妳知道的
can't grant you your request.
我無法回應妳的感情
I want more.
我很想要
Of what?
什麼？
Of you.
我想要你，川合
Congratulations, I'm happy for you.
恭喜你，太好了
I thought I'd find you here.
你果然在這裡
No, you can't.
不可以
Think long and hard.
你仔細想清楚
The more you try to talk to your teacher--
你現在越是來找老師跟她講話…
Hold up.
等一下
The worse you make her situation.
只會讓老師的立場更加難堪
If you really care about her, you can't see her, okay?
如果你重視她 現在就不能見面，好嗎？
Hey!
喂！
Your bike! Akira!
你的腳踏車！阿晶！
Hijiri is being disciplined!
小聖接受處分了
Disciplined?
處分？
Kuroiwa came by and told me.
剛才黑岩告訴我的
Why is she getting disciplined?
她為什麼被處分了？
Does it involve Kuroiwa?
該不會跟黑岩發生什麼事了吧？
Something about his mom catching them together.
像是被他媽看到他們在一起
What, sexual misconduct?
那是怎麼樣，淫行嗎？
Where's Kuroiwa now?
黑岩人在哪裡？
He asked to borrow money.
他跟我借錢
Money? Why?
錢？為什麼？
He wanted to go somewhere.
他說想去一個地方
-My name is Kuroiwa. -Okay.
-我叫黑岩 -是
I'm looking for Mr. Shotaro Kawai from the Construction Department.
請問建設產業部的 川合勝太郎先生在嗎？
Mr. Kawai from where?
你是說哪間公司的川合？
There are a lot of companies in this building, can you tell me which one?
我們這裡有很多公司 請問是哪一家公司？
Oh, right, um…
哦，公司，那個…
You there.
你
Are you Young Kuroiwa?
是黑岩少年嗎？
Here you go.
來
What's this?
這是什麼？
Juice.
綜合果汁
Thank you.
謝謝
You prefer coffee?
你比較喜歡咖啡嗎？
I'm out of touch.
我不太懂你這年紀的人
I barely interact with middle schoolers.
我很少接觸國中生
You saw this and came here?
你是看到這個才跑過來的嗎？
Where is Mr. Kawai?
請問川合先生在哪裡？
Out of the office.
他不在辦公室
Looks like you came for nothing.
看來你白跑一趟了
So Hijiri's being disciplined.
小聖被處分啊
It's my fault.
都是我的錯
So what's your plan when you meet Kawai?
所以跟川合見面之後 你打算怎麼做？
I don't know.
我不知道
Tell him to give you Hijiri?
要叫他把小聖讓給你嗎？
Would that work?
他會讓給我嗎？
I doubt it.
應該不會吧
If I see him,
見了面
then maybe something would change.
也許會有什麼改變
Maybe he'd understand if we talked.
說出來的話，也許他會理解
I did a lot of thinking.
我想了很多
Because
因為
Hijiri is the only one for me.
小聖是我的唯一
You know,
總感覺
that's nice.
那樣真好
Having one person for you.
自己只有這個人
It's nice feeling that way.
那樣感覺真好
It seems like nothing,
好像沒什麼大不了
but it feels like everything.
卻勝於一切
I'm impressed, kid.
你真的很厲害，少年
I'm Akira Kuroiwa.
我叫黑岩晶
You're just a boy.
你還只是個少年
So go home.
所以趕快回家去吧
I'm sure your mom is worried.
你母親想必很擔心你
If you don't leave, I'll call the cops to take you.
若是不走的話，我會叫警察帶你走
If you're frustrated,
如果你不甘心
then grow up fast,
那就趕快長大吧
young lad.
少年
Thank you very much.
謝謝妳
KOBOSHIDAIRA SPORT'S DAY
（子星中學運動會）
Where have you been!
你去哪了？
Akira!
阿晶！
-Let go! -Come on!
-放手！ -跟我過來！
Hurry up!
快點！
If you pull something like this again, I'll call the school board
下次再敢擅自妄為 我就會打電話給教育委員會
and have that woman fired.
馬上開除那個女人
This isn't a bluff.
這可不是騙你的
If she's the reason
如果你變得如此奇怪
you're acting this crazy, then I'll hold her responsible.
變得這麼失控的原因是因為她 那我就要她負起責任
If you don't want that to happen, then stay here
你若不希望事情變成那樣 就給我待在家裡
and sit tight.
給我老實待著
Wait!
等一下！
Okay.
我知道了
I'll do what you say.
我會照做的
I'll study if you say so, and if you tell me to give her up,
要我念書我就念，要我放棄老師的話
then I will.
我就放棄
So please,
所以求求妳
I'm begging you. Don't let Ms. Suenaga quit.
不要逼老師辭職
Please!
求求妳！
I won't do anything until
在接到學校的通知前
we hear from the school.
我什麼都不會做
Please.
求求妳
Iwasaki.
岩崎同學
Good morning.
早安
What's this about?
怎麼了？
Is Ms. Suenaga quitting?
末永老師會辭職嗎？
Who told you that?
是誰說的？
Please tell me.
拜託妳，請告訴我
What happened with her and Kuroiwa?
她跟黑岩怎麼了？
Something scandalous?
是醜聞嗎？
Then she'll have to be fired.
這樣的話，會開除她吧？
It can't be wrong for a male teacher, but okay for a female teacher.
應該不會說男老師犯錯不行 女老師犯錯就沒關係吧
Do you want Ms. Suenaga to quit?
妳希望末永老師辭職嗎？
Probably…
也許…
Yes.
是
But it's not because I hate her.
可是並不是因為我討厭老師
Not that I like her either.
雖說也不是喜歡她
But I feel myself becoming a worse person.
但我覺得自己越來越差勁
I can't stop myself anymore.
我已經無法控制自己了
It's hard.
我很痛苦
Did they decide?
處分出來了嗎？
Yes.
對
They just called.
剛才來通知了
They will be treating my resignation as voluntary retirement.
辭呈會以自願辭職處理
Hijiri.
聖
But
但是
I don't care about that.
我一點也不在乎
What?
什麼？
I'm just
我只是
so sorry for Kuroiwa.
覺得對不起黑岩
I wasn't able to stop
我既無法拒絕
or redirect the feelings he expressed to me.
也沒能回應他對我的心意
And I wasn't able to
也沒能
guide my other students either.
指導其他的學生
I was never suited for this.
我本來就不適合當老師
I will
我不會
never teach again.
再當老師了
So quit and do what?
不當老師要做什麼？
Shotaro told me to come to Osaka.
勝太郎叫我去大阪
But I'd just be taking advantage of his kindness again.
但是我這樣的話，就只是在利用他
I'm trying to decide if I shouldn't go home.
所以我在考慮要不要暫時回老家
Okay.
好
Then let's go.
那我們走
Go where?
去哪裡？
Go and tell your parents.
去跟妳爸媽說吧
That you fell for a student and got fired.
說妳喜歡上學生，然後被學校開除了
Did you actually think?
妳真的有想過嗎？
About how this happened.
為什麼事情會變成這樣
After everything I said, why did you go cross the line?
為什麼我都警告過妳了 妳還是跨越了師生的界線？
I guess that's all being a teacher was to you.
我想當教師對妳來說就不算什麼吧
Something you can easily give up.
是如此輕易就能決定放棄的
Well, if that's the case, go tell your supportive parents
既然如此，妳至少要跟 一直支持著妳的父母
everything that happened.
好好解釋清楚
Hijiri?
聖？
It's been so long, Ms. Chizuru.
千鶴小姐，好久不見
What's the matter, Hijiri?
怎麼啦，聖？
-Where's Dad? -He went to the driving range.
-爸爸呢？ -去打高爾夫球了
After I did all this cooking.
我好不容易煮了一桌菜
Why don't you stay and eat?
對了，妳留下吃飯吧？
Okay.
好
Here.
來了
Come on, sit down.
好了，快坐下
Thank goodness.
太好了
It didn't have to go to waste.
飯菜沒有浪費掉
Here you go.
來
Thank you for the meal.
我開動了
I'm sorry.
對不起
I'm sorry, Mom.
對不起，媽媽
I had to…
我要…
quit the school.
辭職了
The wedding
結婚的事
is probably off.
大概也結不成了
I fell for a student.
我喜歡上學生了
We got caught when we were together,
被人看到我跟他在一起
so I had to leave.
已經待不下去了
Does Shotaro know about this?
勝太郎知道這件事嗎？
Yes.
知道
If Shotaro doesn't mind,
如果勝太郎不介意
you should still get married.
妳還是嫁給他吧
What?
什麼？
If
如果
he's able to forgive you,
如果他願意原諒妳
you should go through with the wedding
妳就照原訂計畫嫁給他
and move to Osaka.
趕快搬去大阪吧
But I--
但我…
You fell for someone else?
妳喜歡上別人了嗎？
Are you going to be with him?
妳要跟他在一起嗎？
It's not impossible.
這也不是不可能哦
You could run away together,
你們一起私奔
and then you could find another job,
妳找另一份工作
and wait until his compulsory education is over.
等他結束義務教育
Once he turns eighteen,
到他十八歲
then you could get married.
就能跟他結婚
Can you picture all that?
妳能想像嗎？
But Shotaro
但是勝太郎
despite knowing everything still asked you to come to Osaka.
即使知道了一切，還是希望妳去大阪
I don't deserve it.
我不配
I'm sure it'll work out.
最後會沒事的
-I can't imagine it. -No.
-我不覺得 -不
It will.
一定會
Because, Hijiri,
因為聖
you'll be forever grateful.
因為妳這輩子都會感謝他
That's what's important.
這點很重要
That you owe a debt to them.
他對妳有恩
The man who saved me and changed my life.
是拯救和改變了妳人生的恩人
That kind of thinking will lead you to a good marriage.
這麼想的話，婚後生活肯定能順利
You can find happiness with Shotaro.
妳跟勝太郎在一起會獲得幸福
You will make him happy.
妳會讓他幸福
I'm cooking, go take a bath.
我來煮飯，妳去洗澡
Wait, what?
等一下，什麼？
It's almost done.
快煮好了
Thank you.
謝謝
Find comfort in food in times like these.
這種時候就該從食物獲得能量
Macrobiotic.
長壽飲食
The way to find balance in your food.
營養均衡的飲食法
Huh…
嗯…
Call me crazy,
信不信由你
but you don't look like a man looking forward to married life.
但你怎麼看都不像是 即將新婚的幸福男子的表情啊
I'm perfectly happy.
我很幸福啊
Kawai, this isn't like you.
川合，這不像你
It's time to stop.
不要這樣了
Your special ability…
你最擅長的…
Turning a blind eye, pretending not to hear,
裝沒看見，裝沒聽見
acting like it's all okay.
裝沒事
You don't need to act tough.
你不需要逞強
Eat, sleep,
吃飯，睡覺
and feel better.
打起精神吧
My competition
我的情敵
is a middle school kid.
可是國中生哦
Thank you for the meal.
我開動了
Akira, I heard you haven't touched your food.
阿晶，聽說你都沒吃飯
Are you on a diet? Or is this a hunger strike?
減肥嗎？還是在絕食啊？
Pardon me.
打擾啦
I brought you your favorites.
這是你最愛吃的
It was for the best.
她這麼做是對的
It's good Ms. Hijiri quit.
還好小聖老師辭職了
She can't rely on a man who gets all sullen like this.
這種只會悶悶不樂的男人 根本不能依靠
No wonder you have everyone worried.
難怪大家會擔心你
If you want people's respect,
如果你想得到大家的認可
then you'd better step up as a man.
那就作為一個男子漢振作點
KANAGAWA HIGH SCHOOL ENTRANCE EXAM GUIDE
（《神奈川縣高中入學考試指南》）
What do you want to be?
你想成為什麼樣的大人？
Imagine the person you want to become, and think of the steps you have to take.
你先想像自己想成為什麼樣的人 然後想想要怎麼做
Can you picture the school?
腦中有浮現想去的學校了嗎？
CAREER ASPIRATION SURVEY
（未來志願調查）
Hijiri? you okay?
聖，妳還好嗎？
Yeah.
很好啊
I'll come pick you up soon.
我最近會去接妳
Come to Osaka
來大阪
and you can start everything over.
妳就可以重新來過了
I'll always be on your side.
我永遠都會站在妳這邊
Thank you.
謝謝
MS. MICHIYO SHIOYA
（鹽谷三千代小姐收）
Huh? Kawai took the day off?
咦？川合請假嗎？
Oh, he said he was going to go pick his girlfriend up.
他去接女友了
He's pretty thorough that way.
那傢伙對這種事很認真
-This as well. -Okay.
-這個也麻煩了 -好的
MIDDLE SCHOOL TEACHING, CAREER GUIDANCE
（《中學教學，未來志願指導》）
Hijiri is leaving!
小聖要走了！
What?
什麼？
I saw a moving truck when I went by Hijiri's place.
剛才我經過小聖家附近 看到搬家公司的貨車
She's leaving today.
她今天就要走了
You need to go!
你快去！
Go see her.
去見她
I admire you for real.
我真的很崇拜你
I never thought Hijiri would look your way.
我原本以為小聖不會理你
I thought your chances were zero.
我以為你的機率根本是零
Go over there
快過去
and nab Hijiri!
去把她搶過來！
Bro friendship attack.
男人間的友情攻擊
Where are you going?
你想去哪裡？
No.
不行
You can't!
你不可以！
Stop!
停下來！
-Why not? -If you go, there's no coming back.
-為什麼？ -你去了就回不來了
Your emotions will overwhelm you, and take over your thoughts.
那樣只會讓情緒更激動 滿心只想著這件事
You'll ruin your life!
你會毀了自己的人生！
-You don't know that! -I do!
-妳不懂！ -我懂！
I was the same!
因為我也是這樣！
Come with me!
跟我來！
There's something I haven't told you.
我有事情沒告訴你
As I told you,
我跟你說過
your father left when you were five.
你爸在你五歲時離家了
Because he was struggling with work, right?
因為工作不順利，對吧？
That's the reason I gave you for our divorce.
我跟你說是因為這樣才離婚
But I
其實是因為
fell in love with someone.
我喜歡上別人了
What?
什麼？
He helped me after your father left.
在你爸離開家裡之後，他幫助我
He was an architect who bought your father's furniture.
他是來買你爸傢俱的建築師
Being with him was fun.
跟他在一起總是很開心
I became obsessed.
全心投入
After the divorce I thought I would move us in with him.
我離婚後，帶著你去和他生活
But he had a family too.
但是他也有家室
It didn't work out.
最後不了了之
I thought I could never recover.
我還以為再也無法振作起來
But you will forget.
但你會忘掉的
No matter how strong your feelings are now, you'll forget with time.
不管現在多麼痛苦 一段時間後就會忘記
It's like suddenly waking from a dream.
會突然從夢中清醒
There is no such thing as a one and only.
沒有什麼所謂的“唯一”
It's just temporary.
這都只是一時的
No matter how much you regret it afterwards, it'll be too late.
到時候，無論你多麼後悔都沒用了
You won't be able to take it back.
一切都會無法挽回
-At your age-- -I'm not like you!
-尤其在你這年紀… -少混為一談！
Don't compare me to your stupid life!
少把我跟妳的蠢事混為一談！
Wait, Akira!
等一下，阿晶！
Akira!
阿晶！
Ready to go?
該走了吧？
Yeah.
好的
You told him about the letters?
妳跟他說信的事了嗎？
I wanted him to listen.
因為我希望他能稍微聽我說話
You think he went to see Ms. Hijiri?
他是去找老師了嗎？
I wish she'd just disappear from our lives already.
真希望她快走
I don't care what anyone says, I love you.
我不在意別人怎麼說，我喜歡老師
Just forget about me, that was a mistake.
你忘了我吧，那樣是不對的
No.
不
It was wrong.
那是錯的
Why?
為什麼？
Because you're fifteen!
因為你才十五歲！
Ms. Haraguchi. Here you go.
原口小姐，來
Thanks.
謝謝
Because Hijiri is the only one for me.
因為小聖是我的唯一
My competition is a middle school kid.
我的情敵可是國中生哦
Seriously…
真是的
What the hell am I doing?
我到底在幹什麼啊？
I'll just be a sec.
等我一下
Hello?
喂？
You're sure?
你確定嗎？
You're okay with all this?
你這樣真的好嗎？
What now?
又怎麼了？
I'm frustrated.
我很不甘心
What?
什麼？
You're better than this.
你不應該這樣
Deep down you're more dependable than you look.
你比看起來可靠得多
But still a little ditzy, yet good at your job.
雖然有些天然呆，但卻很能幹
You are a man with great qualities.
是個很多優點的人
I want you.
我想得到你
I love you.
我喜歡你
But Kawai,
可是川合
you're just acting like a chump trying to keep the two of them apart.
你現在只不過是個 硬要拆散他們的無趣男人
It makes me frustrated.
我很不甘心
You know it deep down.
你也很清楚吧
She found someone.
她遇見了
Hijiri met someone she loves more than you.
小聖遇見了比你更喜歡的人
He's in middle school.
對方可是國中生哦
Yeah, he is.
是啊，他是
So she distanced herself.
所以她才抽身了
But he's the one she loves.
但是她喜歡的是他
If you're happy, then fine.
你如果能幸福，那就無所謂
But if not,
可是如果不幸福
then it's not okay.
那就不行了
Kawai, I'll ask you one more time.
川合，我再問你一次
Are you really okay with all of this?
你這麼做真的不後悔嗎？
Sorry.
對不起
That's…
那個…
"I wanted to express how deeply sorry I am
“再一次向您表達我的歉意
for all the trouble I have caused.
這次惹出這麼大的麻煩
While it was only for one term,
雖然只有一個學期
I was very happy with the time I spent with everyone
我很高興跟大家度過這段時光
as a teacher.
作為一位老師
I loved the sounds
我喜歡學生
of the students in the halls.
迴蕩在走廊的聲音
I loved teaching.
我喜歡教學
I truly admired all the teachers
我也很尊敬各位
dedicated to the students.
對學生孜孜不倦的老師
And yet I ruined everything for myself,
可是我卻親手糟蹋了一切
and I'm truly sorry for it."
真的非常抱歉”
SINCERELY, HIJIRI SUENAGA
（此致，末永聖）
I can't believe she fell for a student.
沒想到她居然會喜歡上學生
She's not suited for the work.
她不適合當老師啊
THE TEACHER I ASPIRE TO BE BY HIJIRI SUENAGA
（我理想中的教師，末永聖）
I wish
我原本希望
I could've taught her more.
能更用心培養她的
Ms. Suenaga!
老師！
Hijiri!
小聖！
Hiji--
聖…
I decided my future!
我決定志願了！
GENERAL COURSE
（西斗一高級中學，普通科 成和高級中學，光洋學園高級中學）
I'm going to
我很快會…
be an adult soon!
成為大人！
So
所以
don't go!
不要走！
Wait!
等一下！
Hijiri!
小聖！
Shotaro.
勝太郎
Stop the car please.
請停車
No, I don't want to hear it now.
不要，我現在不想聽
Please stop the car.
我說了，請停車
I can't go with you.
我還是不能跟你走
As things are
就像這樣
right now
現在這樣
I can't marry you.
我沒辦法嫁給你
Don't tell me
妳該不會
you're going back.
想要回去吧？
I'll never see him again.
我不會再跟他見面了
But being with you in this situation
但是我若以這個狀態跟你在一起
I'd just be taking advantage of you, making things--
就只是在利用你，這樣下去…
And whose fault is it!
這個狀態是誰造成的？
Whose fault is it that we're in this stupid, shameful situation…
是誰造成這麼愚蠢難堪的處境？
You even know what I--?
妳知道我有多…
I'm sorry.
對不起
Then
既然如此
you should be alone
以後妳就變回一個人
and lose everything.
變得一無所有吧
And then
然後
you disappeared.
小聖便消失了
From this town.
從這座小鎮
It was the summer when I was 15
在我十五歲的夏天
when you disappeared.
消失了
Then
然後…
I turned eighteen.
我十八歲了
Subtitle translation by: Zensho Yamamoto
字幕翻譯：楊易